[SPEAKER_02]: I'm actually especially interested in that you said that, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am actually staying actually as background, but that is what I can't see usually, but when it appears, I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, that's not the line, that really unhoused, I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the sense of self, it never appears directionally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if... if it were to appear directly, then you can just say, ah, this is not myself, and that would be the end of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as... like in the suttas, the Buddha say, Putujana takes... with not-self, he takes his self, or with self, takes the not-self, or with self, he takes the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he can never, with not-self, take the not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, whatever Putujana looks, self will be there, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, when people...
[SPEAKER_01]: Try to apply the practice and say, ah, not myself, not myself, to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't work, because it's just like a blanket attitude, that you apply to everything, but that means your sense of self is actually left out, and doing that, applying.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why in the suttas it says, all determinations are impermanent, all determinations are suffering, all things are not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't say all things are impermanent, all things are suffering, all things are not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what most people do.
[SPEAKER_01]: They say, ah, everything is impermanent, everything is not myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's true.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not incorrect to say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not open-eyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't lead on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't bring understanding of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the person needs to include himself into his insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: And doing that is seeing that yourself, your sense of self, depends upon something that is not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you see that your self directly stands upon something that is not yours, then, automatically, that sense of self is not yours either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to then, okay, now I will say to myself, this is not myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your experience, then, is the experience of not-self, if you see determinations of that self as impermanent and as suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why I'm saying, like, it's not, it's not, it's not incorrect to say, oh, nothing is myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, nothing can be yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in terms of the practice, it just doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it can work in terms of making people feel better.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's almost like a form of denial, just saying everything is not myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why it's more important to first recognize that there is a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can never see directly, I can never take it up, I can never say this is not mine and be finished with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to recognize that it's there and then affect your whole experience
[SPEAKER_01]: In your practice, through seeing determination, so then, the whole experience will be experience of not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not just selectively pick and choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everything needs to be effective, because although you might not be able to pinpoint the sense of self, you know for sure that it's within the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you abandon the experience as a whole, you included... that abandoning includes the abandoning of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that was the whole... the whole talking about the...
[SPEAKER_01]: The general background and particular intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're just going out of particular intention, means you don't really see what's in the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if you don't even see what's in the background, you don't even know how to look for the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever you look for the background, you look as if it's particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just make it actual, make it right in front of you, which means something else is a background, which means your sense of self is hiding somewhere else now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to learn to be mindful of the general background without over-intending it and making it into particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's general.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if that's not general, something else will be general.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, learning to do that means, ah, you start to notice more peripherally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without moving your vision left or right, up or down, you just start to include more in what you're already seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if each time you want to see something, you keep moving,
[SPEAKER_01]: Around, you'll end up seeing only that which you move to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that was the whole point of that email and of the sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: What did you mean of the intentional situation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, even that general background is already intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, the intentions are not as defined as they are particularly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I told you then before, a general situation being in this room,
[SPEAKER_01]: It gives you a certain set of particular intentions as possibilities that are allowable in this room.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example, if you go outside, you won't have a chance, you won't be able to intend to use this water filter to drink water, because that's in here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your general situation has changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, okay, drinking water is important.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start modifying your general situation so that particular intentions can arise where you can get the water to drink.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not that intentions only come from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when you think you're intending, the only reason you're able to intend is because your general situation allows you those possibilities that now you are attending and they become intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't create anything, in other words.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't come up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even if you come up with new things, an intention of a new thing is given from their general background.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can only use
[SPEAKER_01]: Or choose between the given set of possibilities based on the general situation, where you are, your abilities, your... and, like, body and bodily predispositions, height, strength, eh... complexion, all of those are form and they partake, or rather, they're fundamental form of a general situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, a short, eh... disabled person cannot have intentions of running marathon.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for him, it's inherently removed from his fundamental situation that's determined by his body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, he can use different set.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can focus on different possibilities that arise and then pursue those directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But either way, all he can do is kind of modify things that are given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't create anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And nobody can.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's not that, kind of, your choice is given for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a responsibility for the choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the possibilities of your choice are given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when you choose between yes and no, well, yes and no are given beforehand as a form of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you choose one on account of the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's basically your intentionality that chooses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by attending
[SPEAKER_01]: By attending the reason for choosing yes, you choose yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: By attending the reason to choose no, you choose no.
[SPEAKER_01]: By, you know, giving in to the external pressure or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Various factors that affect your choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not your me that is... because arahant still has a choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he doesn't have a sense of self anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, sense of self interferes and takes credit for these things that happen by himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's important to first see that, and then take responsibility for your choice, as if it is you who is choosing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the only way you can actually, through that, abandon the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't see that, and then immediately start saying, well, I haven't...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not doing anything, it's just this body and everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the denial.
[SPEAKER_01]: For Putrajana, that's the denial.
[SPEAKER_01]: So Putrajana first has to admit that he is,
[SPEAKER_01]: That he's choosing, that he's responsible, that there are results of his actions, that there is mother, there is father, there is killing, there is giving life, there is all of that, like the mundane right view the Buddha talks about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once he's able to admit that, to see that, then he can begin abandoning sense of self through that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without abandoning that view, he abandons his sense of self based on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But usually people kind of take a shortcut, and then they they go straight into saying, well, everything is not self,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nobody's doing any action anyway, and so on and so forth, which is actually similar to the wrong views of the Buddha's time that he was often discussing.
[SPEAKER_01]: When people would say, well, there is no door, there is no good or bad, it's just elements and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason why that is wrong is because there is a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a mistake, but it's real as a mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, denying a mistake means you'll never be able to solve the mistake, to correct it, to rectify it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you deny it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first, you have to admit that there is a mistake, and then you'll be able to fix it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but, but,
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those things still stay.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the ownership is a confusion, thinking that it's me, it's mine, I'm doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's very much a different point, because, as I observe, I think it's a choice, a choice, A or B.
[SPEAKER_02]: They are given.
[SPEAKER_02]: But which one I choose, that one actually appears as thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you are responsible for accepting that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a decision, as a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, the thought appeared.
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't create it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you do choose, you do accept to go with it or not go with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if the thought appears, you can't say the choice has been made for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You always make the choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by doing that, by recognizing that, then you can disown yourself making the choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not deny yourself making the choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a big difference there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the difference is in that order of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you admit that there is a mistake, and then, through the admittance of mistake, you can rectify the mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the second, the denial, is different.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically, you see there is a mistake, and then, you deny the mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, ah, it's not mine, doesn't exist, it's all fixed already, not a problem, we're all in nibbāna, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you don't see the mistake anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think you fixed it, but actually, you just obscured it
[SPEAKER_01]: So, taking up responsibility for your choice, like really feeling responsible, like, I am doing this, I am choosing this, that is the first step.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through that, you can abandon sense of I, without abandoning responsibility for the action.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you overcome the action, finally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for as long as you're avoiding responsibility for it, you're avoiding the nature of action, which means you're not overcoming the khandhā.
[SPEAKER_01]: The choice is there, and there is a mistake of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's real, as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to accept it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you'll be able to fix it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was thinking that karma, how do you view in the case of Putrajana, actually?
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course, in the case of Putrajana, of course, that I am, I am the one making karma.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the mistake he's making, the karma, which is why Pratyūjana remains bound to saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a real thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he finds out that it's a mistake, it ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's free.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, it's not just an illusion or something like that, because saṃsāra is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: And results of the saṃsāra are very real.
[SPEAKER_01]: And results of one's actions are very, very real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you read in the Sutta, sometimes people did
[SPEAKER_01]: A little thing that was wrong, but then it resulted in a lot later on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's never a guarantee, thinking, oh, I'll be fine or not, which means that responsibility is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for as long as the person doesn't admit the mistake, the misunderstanding, misappropriation, he won't be able to fix it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes people are too keen to fix it, so they quickly fall into denial of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not self, not self, not mine, not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: The science has proved nothing is self, nothing is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that just obscures, that doesn't accept the responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start saying to yourself, not self, not mine, through the acceptance of that responsibility and never abandoning that responsibility, that's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But usually people do that, they say to themselves, not self, in order to avoid the responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it feels like a fix, but it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's a temporary fix, which means it doesn't really work in the long term.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do I... disowning the... accepting it is... it is...
[SPEAKER_02]: I am the one...
[SPEAKER_02]: I am responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, disowning...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I use that word, but it's not... it's not like you don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, I don't own this anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You disown it,
[SPEAKER_01]: By seeing that you cannot own it in the first place, by finding out that it's actually impossible to be owned, not knowing that it's impossible to own something, just because you don't know that it's impossible, that's why you own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, finding out that actually, own or not, just makes no difference to the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot access, it cannot master, you cannot be the master of it, nor control it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Automatically, you, you kind of, you stopped owning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you say, oh, this is my book, this is my chair, this is my phone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Internally, you don't own anything because you saw through the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... it was the case in the suttas as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: When people focus on designations and they think, oh, you shouldn't be saying mine or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, the Tathāgata uses the word I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for him, it doesn't mean anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Certainly, it doesn't mean what it means for Putuja.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same for mine and
[SPEAKER_01]: Belonging to me and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically the internal connection is what matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, people can go around saying, not mine, not mine, yet hold tightly on to everything, because they don't know the way out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another person might not pay any attention to what he says, but internally, he won't own anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that's very interesting that they even, in the case of Arahant, I feel
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is going wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, from outside, no one can see that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because everything's the same way going on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But he knows everything's not his.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only there's a difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: And some people think, like, an arahant means they don't fear and they don't, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: He flies in the clouds or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you read the suttas and even the other arahants sometimes wouldn't be able to recognize another arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be a bit harder.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha could do it instantly, or some other monks with greater powers, but generally, yeah, you had to talk to the person, you had to see what their view was.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha was saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, don't ever leave anything unturned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you should question, interrogate each other, look for the meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the meaning is not clear, press further until the meaning is clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: See where your understanding is, see what other monks understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how both parties learn.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is a genuine knowledge,
[SPEAKER_01]: That is being pushed further and further, not just a theoretical debate or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not just that they were talking.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means, by knowing each other's views, knowing where they are, they could tell, oh, he's an arahant, or he's probably very soon going to be an arahant, or, oh, he's far from an arahant, but if he makes enough effort, he will be one, and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was very interesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: You said that, actually, like, many people think, like, we were born, like, to hear, to see, and to smell, and to taste, and
[SPEAKER_02]: Even that is... that is also not the reason, actually.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's also really interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not born for anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, for nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just misunderstanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: The ideal purpose comes from... already from that mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think the Buddha said, probably on a few occasions, but I remember the one instance when he was saying that because a person takes what is not his, he makes use out of it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, he basically owns... well, you become indebted to Mara and then Mara can do with you whatever he wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by using things that belong to Mara, you're in Mara's control.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they ask him, well, what are those things?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, it's the sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, eye, nose, all of the senses and sense bases are Mara's domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means they're not yours to begin with, your own eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't belong to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're there.
[SPEAKER_01]: They do the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Purpose of looking or whatever else, but none of that obliges you to take them as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only not knowing that they are not yours, you automatically take them as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why even a newborn baby is already affected by a vijja.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although it didn't grow out, it didn't develop designation and stuff, the structure, the mind structure and the mentality, intentionality, it's already there, just waiting to develop.
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, all intentions are arising.
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, they're like a... want to... want to hear, want to see... Well, everything is intentional in that sense, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just removing or rather seeing that the center of intention is not in you or mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because things are already intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the only reason intention can be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to see that through accepting responsibility for your choices, for your intentions, not through denying it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or not in order to deny it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not denying, but actually, must keep observing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, I think that everything, our intention, everything's actually arriving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you know, like, not, not everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just whatever's present at the moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the present intentions and present general situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what's important.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start thinking, oh, everything is everything, is that all?
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you've fallen onto a view that everything is intentional and everything is like this or everything is like that and everything is not myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that leaves a particular intention in general, in particular sort of order of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see it, because you're thinking about your view of everything and everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The difference is, your particular intentions and your particular situation should be your foundation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the view that everything is intentional and everything is not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can think everything is intentional and everything is not-self, if you're already anchored in your present situation, like general situation and particular intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Think certain views.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is starting from the general situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, everything is starting where you are just saying that everything is starting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Intentions arising from general.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentions, as I gave you that simile, they're sort of channel directed by the general situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, within that, you can have more particular intentions, but that's all because general situation is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the general situation changes, the particular set of intentions will have to change as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that before, I asked about the support to some people, even when they stay in the temple, sometimes they get like a
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say general situation, when I gave a simile of that slog, don't mistake that for external circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it can correspond, it can be prompted by that, but it corresponds more correctly to moods that people are in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Happy mood, sad mood, depressed mood, fearful mood, non-fearful mood, elated mood,
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a general situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already channeling your intentions, your thoughts, your decisions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're in a bad mood, you don't like anybody that day.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're in a good mood, you like everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can get bad news, it won't affect you, because you're in a good mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the moods change.
[SPEAKER_01]: The general, that general situation you're rooted in, changes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when that changes, then your particular response changes as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to learn, well, you have to start seeing the impermanence of the mood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your mood, do you mean the general situation?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your general situation is when your mood is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Heidegger was talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said that the design's mode of being is... the more general mode of being is a mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your first relationship with the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when I say first, I mean structurally first, not linear, not temporarily first.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean one, two, three, but your mood is at the same time there when your particular intentions and actions are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it comes first in terms of comes before.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already a form of relating with the world, interacting with the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're in a bad mood because of something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you're in a good mood, well, maybe because of nothing in particular, but it's still a form of relationship with the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means that that mood, that situation you're in, will be determining your particular intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you become mindful of that, you are mindful automatically of whatever you do particularly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in return, through developing that mindfulness, you will be less and less affected by your own moods.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the less you're affected by your own moods, the less of moods they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suppose some people, for example, ten people stay in the same situation, or put in the same place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Externally, it looks the same, but internally, their mood situation might be very different.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might have different reasons they're doing it, different motivation,
[SPEAKER_01]: It affects them differently, which means their moods will be different.
[SPEAKER_01]: Their minds will be at different stage, at different level.
[SPEAKER_02]: Reacting in different way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being in a different way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even... just being in a different way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suppose in the temple, suppose ten monks are there, but at least one or two of them, sometimes they might not be having some like a wholesome thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: But general situation is same in the temple, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, again, general situation is not the external circumstances of the temple.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the general situation of them wanting to be in the temple for various reasons that they came to the temple.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, general situation, as much as particular situation, for that matter, is actually rooted in you, in your actions, in your intentions, not in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, the monastery will offer certain intentionality as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that are there, monks that are there, but again, all of that is experienced internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't say, oh, they're all in the same situation, why would they react differently?
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're in your own situation, that's all you can know about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can see that somebody else is in a bad mood, or good mood, or indifferent mood, and you can say, ah, there is a bad mood externally, there is a good mood externally, there is a depression externally, there is a depression internally, if you're depressed or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see these things, but again, it's all in relation to the mind, not in relation to the things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in relation to the objects or buildings or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: How each person reacts differently?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the situation, the rooted situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, they can be experiencing the same things, but if their mind is rooted in different mood, so to speak, they will be acting differently.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or they will be acting for different reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or they will be intending different things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although it externally looks the same,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's done for different reasons, which means it's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not necessarily that somebody's making lots of offerings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, he's a very nice person, because he might be doing it for bad reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, he still will have some benefit from making offerings anyhow.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not ideal, but it's better than not doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you really want to do it properly, you want to make the offering and do it for the right reasons.
[SPEAKER_02]: I want to make it clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: The, the, the, the, the, the way you explain that, the general situation, situation means the, the, the place, well... No, no situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, see, when you say situation means the place, you let lead yourself out, and then you try to reintroduce yourself into that situation, and see how can you react differently based on the same situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's a mistake, because actually you can't separate yourself from the situation in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you say situation is the place, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to say situation is me being in a certain place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't leave yourself out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, me being in the monastery, you being in the monastery, Kanye being in the monastery, anybody being in the monastery, they have a thing that is in common to it, which is being in the monastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the me part is different to all of us.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because we came for different reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can be the same if we are here for the same reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't just focus on the place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because place without you is meaningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a move.
[SPEAKER_02]: You mean that the situation means?
[SPEAKER_01]: You mean that the... Means how you feel in a certain place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where your mind is in a certain place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Generally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, based on that, you must be making and doing particular actions and choices.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, their situation has things in common.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't come from the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't say, oh, they're all in the same place and they react differently.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, they're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Their places correspond by having in common that they're all in the monastery, but the internal aspect of it, me, my mood, my mind, my feelings, that's unique to all the aggregates individually, which is why there's difference between individuals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even in terms of arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so you can't separate yourself and think that the place is the situation and then try to explain it to yourself back.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you are already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Already connected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you're part of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... you're inseparable from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just... it wouldn't make any... it would be inconceivable to think you're apart from it, unless it's based on a mistake.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means that that mood... that is... that is a general...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mood is, you know, it's not... like, you know, I can be...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can be in a bad mood, but particularly I can be doing good things, if I... if I don't allow myself to be moved by my bad mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: But generally, the bad mood is there, and it's kind of directing me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I might be doing good things because I want to counter my bad mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still... that's prompted by my bad mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that general slope is there, and then I'm kind of going down it and choosing things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can always choose wholesome on account of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're in the worst possible mood, there is never a justification for unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, when the mood changes, your particular thing might change, or might not, if you have enough wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you develop enough wisdom to keep choosing wholesome over unwholesome, keep attending wholesome thoughts over unwholesome, despite how you feel,
[SPEAKER_01]: How much pull you experience, how much bad bad influence you get from the world or whatever, it's never...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you choose to do bad, it's because you've chosen to do bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've chosen that to be the reason for your bad action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you've chosen that to be a good reason for your good action.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're always responsible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter how bad the mood is, you...
[SPEAKER_01]: You are always responsible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is important to start seeing it first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you don't see the general background of your mood, of the direction your mind is in, you will not see a responsibility in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've just been moved.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have people who, when they're in a bad mood, they say things to people, they say out loud, they offend people, they hurt people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then they feel bad afterwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they kind of come out of the bad mood, they apologize.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'll never do that again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then they do it again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you have people, when they're in a good mood, they're so excited, ecstatic, they get a bit too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then afterwards, they feel a bit, oh God, I got a bit carried away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they're not aware of the general situation, of the general direction of their mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, by not being aware, they don't have a safeguard, so they're always taken by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if before you experienced that mountain and that slope and that's already included means that mood, that itself was a mood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not something like a... No, not the actual location.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that is the reason that some people, even when they stay in the temple, their mood is not not good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can be sitting right next to the Buddha and still... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There were cases like, like they, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: In the assembly of the Buddha, but they just would not.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind wouldn't be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they say, well, you're wasting the opportunity.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, it doesn't necessarily mean much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, going to a place of the temple can remind you, oh, well, it can remind you if you were to know what you're supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you were to know that you're supposed to be mindful of your moods and take responsibility for your choices,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, going to a monastery or reading the suttas can remind you of that when you forget.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't know that in the first place, well, no amount of visits to the monastery will make a difference, because you can't be reminded of something that you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you'll probably get different things then in the monastery, and people will go for different reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: For a monastery, superstition or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Usually, it's a superstition.
[SPEAKER_01]: But regardless of the religion as well, whether it's Buddhism or Christianity, it's all usually... That's the reason why people go to churches and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's quite hard to maintain mindfulness with thinking about the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because you're trying to maintain mindfulness in a particular sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're trying to keep it in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness is knowing the background without interfering with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I ask you now, are you in a good or a bad mood?
[SPEAKER_01]: You will know the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not be able to define it specifically, but you will know, it's all right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, no, I'm not too good.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that knowledge is already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means no need to see the place where I'm in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the mood that I have to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the fact that you can give me the answer to where your mood is, at any time, means that knowledge is there at any time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Already the situation is included.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's something which can be mind... Only that is necessary to be mindful of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Before, I remember you said that I'm sitting in the cave, kuti, and something, something.
[SPEAKER_02]: You were explaining about situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it included in all those inclinations?
[SPEAKER_01]: I am sitting, I am doing, I am means, yeah, means basically you are in such and such situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means your mood is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is it important to see that I am sitting in the kuti?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it important?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that was just the example I gave you, as a more general situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I am in the monastery now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be mindful of, I am, I'm feeling elated now, or I'm feeling depressed now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, like in satipaṭṭhāna, when the Buddha refers to the mind, he says, he knows mind, like, literally, for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows elated mind as elated mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows depressed mind as depressed mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Happy mind as happy, expanded mind, shrunk mind, like different shapes the mind can take.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows them, but that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not trying to change it or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just, ah, the mind is in that state, which means it will be affecting my particular choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the mind is in depressed mood, you're mindful of it, you will be more aware of the choices you make, which means you will not be making bad choices, because you know that the mind will be trying to get you to make the bad choices, because the mind is depressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, when the mind is happy,
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be overreaching in terms of your great choices, because you know, the mind is elated, which means the perspective is a bit lost.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to have the mind even, but, like, even an arahant will practice mindfulness in terms of the different shapes his mind will take.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that he completely, completely severed any bond with that mind, or with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whichever shape his mind takes, it doesn't affect him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, he's gone beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: But until that's the case, you need to keep that in mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're only aware or mindful of what's in front of you, it means you're not seeing your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your mind is never in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always in the back.
[SPEAKER_02]: I admit that seeing situation is in front of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you're seeing situation in front of you, that's not your situation anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Situation is where the mind is, which is always in the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mood is where the mind is, which is always in the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you try to see it in front of you, it means whatever you're seeing in front of you is not the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it was the background before, the fact that you put it in front means something else is now.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means only us to keep seeing the... like a mood, like a mental state.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you have to keep seeing the relationship between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to keep seeing the mood, the mental state, and the relationship between your particular situation, like particular choices you make.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, this intention... Means, things I'm about to do, based on how I feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, to put it simply, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I feel good, I feel bad, I feel neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I doing right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whatever you do, actually, is rooted in how you feel.
[SPEAKER_02]: Bodily feeling or, I don't know, suppose there's something that I feel each year that is... No, those are not feelings, those are all perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, each is a perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might dislike... you might dislike your itch.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, experience displeasure in your mind on account of the bodily itch, but it's not that you're experiencing displeasure in your body as a sensation.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's just a perception of touch.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pain is feeling, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain is feeling, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pain is perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, itch can be painful or sometimes itch can be pleasant, depending on whatever people are into.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pain, I think you say that, the unprisoned feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, pain is unprisoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every feeling is mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people misunderstand.
[SPEAKER_01]: They think, because when Buddha said, ah, there are bodily feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he said the feelings caused in regard to the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So people misunderstand that and use that to explain sensation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, that's my bodily feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every feeling is cetāsika, is the Pali word, means belonging to... it's mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's in regard to the body, then it's called bodily feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still a mental feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's in regard to the mind, then it's kind of doubly mental feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But either feeling being in regard to body or mind, it's mental in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, when you have a bodily itch, bodily discomfort, you will most likely experience mentally unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not that unpleasant feeling is in your leg.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a very sharp sensation of severed leg and a kind of almost almost unbearable pain mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're mentally free from that pain, that discomfort ceases to cause you suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why that's why like the...
[SPEAKER_01]: The arahants who have their minds developed in terms of jhānas, they could bear a lot of physical discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't be discomfort for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the way the mind relates to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the Buddha asked Mahākassapa, said, ah, well, you're very old now, you've done what there's to be done, why don't you come with me?
[SPEAKER_01]: I get lots of offerings, I get silk robes, stay in these palaces, so you can come and stay with me, because there's no need for you to be living rough in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, oh, there's no need, Lord, because whoever can obtain jhānas and will, like these rag robes and these forests, will feel like the, you know, the softest, highest, most pleasant dwellings and abidings, because that's how it feels to the mind, that is strength in jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, another occasion, when the Buddha was instructing a very well-known ruler, when he said, develop jhānas so that the head robes you're wearing will feel like silk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Developed jhāna so that the sleeping under the root of tree will feel like sleeping in a plastered palace.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, oh, developed jhāna so that the rough, unclean rice you eat would feel like the softest rice with the nicest curries.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it was for medicine and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Saying, basically, that the mind state, the mind development will determine your relationship with your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the body is going through discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, whether you're gonna suffer... Well, whether it... Usually, discomfort is associated with pain, mental pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if there is no discomfort, there is no pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Associated with mental pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experiencing suffering in regard to discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody dislikes discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you develop your mind, means less and less thing will be discomfortable to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Arahants, they have unpleasant feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: They do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can still...
[SPEAKER_01]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, arahant can be an arahant without being mastered all of the jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you had arahants who were in great pain physically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experiencing sharp, piercing sensations, piercing perceptions on account of which...
[SPEAKER_01]: But they were not suffering internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was no dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's just that their relationship with the body was kind of unbearable and pointless, because they were arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: They had no reason to endure all of those sharp discomforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But discomfort in itself is not actually painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the the mental resistance in regard to that makes you suffer on account of discomfort, makes you fear discomfort, makes you really work hard to not experience discomfort.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wait a minute.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anahant, they feel unpleasant feelings, but not suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, relatively speaking, like, you can't say that, because if you say for Pūtūjana that he feels unpleasant feelings, you can't use the same designation for an anahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, from a spiritual point of view, Arahant doesn't have any feelings anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has overcome them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the fact that he doesn't feel anything anymore, that's what's pleasant for him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what Sariputta said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to distinguish the bodily discomfort from pain, from displeasure, from dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because being able to bear discomfort,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sometimes it's necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why for some people asceticism would work.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will make them see things rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not for everyone, but for some people it would.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why the Buddha said, well, if your greed, aversion and delusion decreases while doing ascetic practices, then do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's not decreasing, then don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, some people do need to go through discomfort in order to start to see the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: The discomfort is not automatically a pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your mental resistance in regard to it, that makes you suffer, makes you confused.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by overcoming that, you overcome discomfort, and then you don't fear it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as the Buddha did, he... well, he was the Buddha, so he completely overcome... he didn't have to pursue discomfort anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: What for?
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, he was not affected by it, so he would just go wherever he was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes he would sleep on a stack of hay, under the tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes he would sleep in a king's palace.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's where he was at the time, got invited or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not... it's not the external things will determine, necessarily, whether it's good or bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically your attitude in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, sometimes people can go and live roughly in the forest and under the root of a tree for completely wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't see this difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just torturing themselves and thinking that through torture, they will be developing purification and strength.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: They'll develop endurance, but misguided endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the endurance has to be rooted in right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, anything has to be rooted in right view in order to be right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why a person shouldn't go to a forest and start exerting himself unless it's a sotāpanna, unless he has jhānas, unless other establishments have been made.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, you just end up doing it for unwholesome reasons.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in your answer, it's actually a very difficult point to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because sometimes I feel that because of the self-view, that they try to go against, like, try to change the things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that is actually based on the self-view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, like, again, even if it is based on the self-view, it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have a thought of wanting to change things, that's something you include in your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it came from yourself, from the mistake of yourself or not, it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just experienced it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't divide.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this came from this.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: This came from...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want to... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you experience, it's real as that experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's an abstract experience of something that you've never seen, taste, touch, you experienced it in your mind as such, and it's real in that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're having
[SPEAKER_01]: Resistance in regard to endurance, that's part of the endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have thoughts of resisting this, that's all result of you enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just include it in endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arahant can endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But Arahant won't suffer on account of his endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: He won't fear the endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: He won't try to avoid it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it comes, it comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it doesn't, it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: He won't try to avoid it, but he won't go after it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he has no need for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, it needs to be done for the wholesome reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, patujana can endure a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, there are people who set themselves on fire, complete misguided patujanas, for ridiculous political reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, how dumb is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely misguided.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it's extreme for endurance and people do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that means nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if somebody would endure very little for the right reasons, he would reap much more benefit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you endure because the endurance has arisen, because you don't go after it, nor do you run away from it, nor do you do anything on account of it, that's already more wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can know endurance for what it is, or lack of it for what it is, or need of development for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be running away from it, because sometimes people get really into endurance as a form of running away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I fear this, so I'm going to go and face it, because I'm terrified of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, they end up torturing themselves, as if that will kind of make them overcome the fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is any wisdom in regard to it, it might help them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, putting themselves in a rough situation might help them, if there is a wisdom basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if there isn't, it will just make them revolve around the same issue.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes, actually, even when... even when we don't do anything, automatically, body starts moving, and sometimes it's quite interesting, sometimes just sitting, and not thinking to do anything, but ultimately the body starts moving, it starts doing, it starts thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, it carries on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But really, there is no suffering, but eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's basically, as I said, the body doesn't need self to operate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentions don't need self to operate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they've been operating on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before, for putusana, or after, for anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is, putusana first needs to accept the responsibility for himself,
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is done through developing mindfulness in regard to body and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actions, choices, specifically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, through accepting the responsibility, you can eventually reach a point when you just see, oh, yeah, the intentionality doesn't require sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all operating.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start doing it before you fully accept responsibility, then it will more be like more forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You forgot to be mindful and, yeah, the body is just doing things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's all rooted in our wholesome, because of the self-view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, Arahant's forgetfulness, so to speak, is different from the forget... like, Arahant's forgetfulness will not induce self-view, will not induce a vijaya, which means, basically, it's not really forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for Kuntujan, I mean, he is forgetful, means he forgets all the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how the vijaya ignorance is maintained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, so to speak, but the thing is, like, if your forgetfulness is not inducing a vision, it means you're mindful of you being forgetful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might be forgetful in terms of particular things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I forgot the number or something, but I didn't forget the nature of forgetting.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Arahant's mindfulness is sort of fully developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he can't stop doing it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's always mindful in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he's not always mindful in a sense of contemporary vipassana, like touching, moving, like a robot.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means he can't forget his forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Forgetfulness will not induce avijja anymore for him.
[SPEAKER_01]: So even when he forgets particular things, as an experience of forgetting, he's mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that same cannot be said for patrujya.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, sometimes you even think, I'm not mindful, actually, everything is going well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, whether you're mindful or not, things are intentional and they're going.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing is, you do have to accept responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's why the... that's why the situation of putusana is kind of perilous.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, you're not in control of everything, of anything, but in the same way, you're responsible for everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't control anything, but you have full responsibility for all of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's true.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because patujanā, he might say, oh, well, I'm not doing this and it's just my body.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact is, when he dies, he'll be reborn again, because he's patujanā, and because of the actions he made.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if my body just made these actions, you will be experiencing those results, because you took that body to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, he needs to fully accept that responsibility, even for accidents, even for things that are not in his control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Clear?
[SPEAKER_01]: And through fully accepting the responsibility, he can eventually overcome it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, that's where the mundane right view comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like admitting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ārya is free from karma?
[SPEAKER_02]: Arahant is free from karma, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, Ārya has a limited left over.
[SPEAKER_02]: Really, very good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sotāpanna, is he free from karma?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, relatively.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ultimately, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within seven, at most.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he'll be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he still has
[SPEAKER_01]: The wheel didn't quite stop spinning yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it will.
[SPEAKER_02]: Without self-view, there's calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_02]: Without self-view.
[SPEAKER_02]: They have no self-view.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't believe in self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but they still have residues of conceit.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't have a self-view in terms of thinking of themselves as living
[SPEAKER_01]: Like an independent master of five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have that anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they still have conceit, sense of I am, and they still have degree of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of which, they will be revolving a bit longer, until they make enough effort, whether in this life or...
[SPEAKER_01]: But Sarvabhaṇa doesn't necessarily have to be born seven times.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can become another in his second lifetime, or third, or fourth, or fifth.
[SPEAKER_01]: At most, seven.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it's very difficult to understand the perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: Perception is very difficult to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Perception means a lot like helping, knowledge to arise, no?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, perception means perceiving, means things that arise, means things that you...
[SPEAKER_02]: In the case of pain, you said pain is feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And perception means you said very like I am... Well, what is causing the pain?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the cause of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not necessarily the cause of pain, but basically, perception and feeling are inseparable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just perceive or just feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you feel, you're perceiving something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you're perceiving something, you're feeling something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you say, I have a feeling of pain, well, there is a perception in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Usually, it's what caused your pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what if I testify you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's a sharp, piercing perception that you don't want to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not necessarily pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody tells you, if you touch this fire, I will, I don't know, save 500 dying children, and you go and touch the fire, and you'll be very happy that you've done it, because you know you save 500 lives.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you won't be suffering on account of touching the fire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you want... if you're...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know, if you're a painter, living out of your painting, and then you burn your hand, and you can't paint, you can't earn anymore, your family is suffering, you'll be suffering a lot on account of touching the fire.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same perception, touching the fire.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, perception instead of touching the fire?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's a bodily perception of touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing... seeing something disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can see something disagreeable or agreeable, but you don't have to neither suffer nor be happy on account of it, but usually people are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, I see something agreeable, I like it, I want more of it, you get very elated.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see something disagreeable, well, I don't want to look at it, I don't like it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you have no choice but to look at it, you'll start suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that if I... if I call it pain, it becomes a bit different, because I... like a... like a bodily pain, but actually it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I was telling you, when you told me that, oh, getting rid of the bodily pains or whatever, I said, well, that's... that's irrelevant, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: That has nothing to do to the nature of suffering, to dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, I have a pain in my right arm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, first of all, it's not in your right arm.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's discomfort in your right arm.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of which, your mind is bothered.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you think the pain is in your right arm, then fixing your right arm will feel like you fixed your pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're actually trying to fix your dukkha at a completely wrong domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're trying to... and lots of meditation that people teach is about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or observing the sensations and feeling your body like this, and if it feels tight, you loosen.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's utterly relevant in every possible way.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you see that, eh, what it means, the Goenka?
[SPEAKER_02]: Goenka to make...
[SPEAKER_01]: It could not be more...
[SPEAKER_02]: I, I attended before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it could not be more misguided.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's completely misprojected.
[SPEAKER_01]: I, many people...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's exactly what I'm saying just now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you, you, you look in a completely wrong place for a solution to the problem of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Many people believe Goenka is the arahant or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: People believe various things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason why, why people feel it works is because most of the people that do it
[SPEAKER_01]: Our lay people, with very busy lives, and then, you never really stop, you never really reflect, you don't really have any right views.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you go to a place of an intense retreat, controlling it, with every moment this kind of tech, tech, you do this, you do this, you do this, you watch, you watch... And it almost feels like a release.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the release comes from the novelty, from this new kind of compressed thing, that then brings out the release.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's nothing to do with wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you develop wisdom in regard to it,
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not be on account of Goenka's techniques.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be on account of you practicing understanding, trying to understand, trying to find out what understanding means.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you do, you realize you don't have to do Goenka.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not more than go out by yourself and start sweeping leaves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or carry bricks, if you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is like the treading, treading, seeing, following, keep observing, and going... Yeah, it's all based on body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Based on body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you observe bodily sensations, which is
[SPEAKER_01]: You ordered your contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't feel your body, you perceive it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can experience feelings in your mind in regard to what body is going through, especially if you identify with your body of material form, you'll suffer even more then.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, any suffering that happens or not, happens on the level of mind, not on the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, removing a particular knee pain,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... it's plain ridiculous, when it comes to understanding the nature of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, why would this be relevant in any way?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, just stretch your knee if it hurts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the end of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, because the method says only one thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It says the body is changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: This incontinence may be taken.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, they say the body is changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that sense, it's constantly changing, like a constant flow.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not true.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's changing on one level, but on another level, it's still the same body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if the body is constantly changing, every second becoming different body, you wouldn't be able to refer to it as the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be able to use the same designation for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that you can say it's still the same body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means that change that the Buddha talks about is slightly more complex than just saying it's all impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And modern science has proven that atoms and electrons are constantly changing, so everything is in a constant change.
[SPEAKER_01]: If everything is constantly changing, there is no change at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in order for change to be perceived, there has to be a part that's not changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you can't say it's changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, saying the body is constantly changing is a contradiction in terms, or a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's changing on one level, while still remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, old Mayukha is the same Mayukha that was young Mayukha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, there is a difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body, you know, grew bigger, got older, and so on, but it's still the same body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, change, or rather, as in the Vedas, called invariant under-transformation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or means persisting, while changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Persisting the same, while it's changing on another level.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, Venerable Yāngyur, he said, like, eh... he was looking at the pen, at the hand, at holding the pen, and this is something that, eh... is it same or different?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it the same, that the thing, he was speaking, like, body's changing in form and something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, well, I don't really remember that context, but I think...
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, like, like, eh... he was looking at the pen, that he was holding the pen in his hand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it the same or different?
[SPEAKER_02]: I remember that Venerable Bhārata, he explained, like, that the ship, that there's some part of the ship that is gradually replacing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And is it the same ship or another?
[SPEAKER_01]: I see what you mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was slightly different, though.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think there was a different context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I was talking about the pen.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was about the intention to write the letter, the intention to go with the meaning and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in a way, that's what I was telling you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe last week, I don't remember when it was, when I said, when you designate a thing, that designation is part of a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you refer to something as a ship, you designate a certain collection of things as a ship.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes you can change parts so much, that it becomes a different ship.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if your designation was on the level of a ship,
[SPEAKER_01]: Means it still stays the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because although it's all different parts, it's still a ship.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, if you start putting car parts onto a ship, and then you turn it into a car, you can't say it's a ship anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, oh, it's a car now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it has changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that change is external.
[SPEAKER_01]: That change has nothing to do with the impermanence of determinations that the Buddha is talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sabha, saṅkhara, anicca is nothing to do with that, because this is just something you observe with your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, the curtains have faded, the door is broken.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is not irrelevant is your mood in regard to it, your feelings in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if that door was a very important door, given to you by a very important person, handcrafted, it would be a very valuable door.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it gets broken, you suffer, because the whole significance is affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you were attached to it, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But saying that the door is constantly changing, makes no difference to the fact that it is significant and it means a lot to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether it's changing or not, your... the significance of the door or of any object that you're attached to, remains unaffected.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can be trying to repeat, no, no, it's all changing, it's all changing, it's all changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still, it means a lot to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by saying, it's all changing, it's all changing, you're basically trying to deny the fact that it means a lot to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead of taking responsibility, that it means a lot to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And through accepting responsibility for different amounts of meanings, so to speak, different significance, like, I don't care much about this sheet, but I care about a water filter, because it's more important to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's normal.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's different levels of intentionality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But me trying... it's all changing, it's all changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's trying to deny all of that, thinking that's the escape from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: The escape is... first step is to admit that there are things that mean differently to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something... sometimes something means more, sometimes it means less.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you want to accept that responsibility for the different significance and then overcome it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, become stronger than the strongest significance you're experiencing in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're feminine, usually.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like... that's something like everybody's usually attached.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't help but being attached to your family, to your children.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can deny it, but it won't free you from the attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will just cause denial, saying, that's not really my child.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's your child.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he's changing while remaining your child.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how things work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to be able to fully accept responsibility for death-freeing your child, for all the feelings you have, fully accept responsibility, and then become stronger than that responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when that child is taken away from you, one way or the other, your mind will not go with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not through denying that that was your child, but through becoming stronger than any significance you can gather from the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: Become stronger, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Means not being moved by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if this door is very important to me, it was a gift made, whatever,
[SPEAKER_01]: I acknowledge all that and I fully accept that and full responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, if somebody asked, does this door mean more than that room?
[SPEAKER_01]: I would say, yes, it's more important and it was a gift by a good friend or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: He made it specially for me and made lots of effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a... it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's no point in... there's no reason to deny that, unless I believe the denial of that would free me from my attachment to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to free myself from the attachment of the important external object, is through overcoming the significance of the external object without denying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to admit that it's important and then become more stronger than that importance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the importance is taken away, when the thing that is important is taken away, you're not affected.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as the mundane right view says, to repeat again, there is mother, there is father.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't go around saying, oh, no, it's just a collection of atoms and everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no mother, there is no father, there is nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what Goenka said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means Goenka is not even a mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he was just one of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Really, there's so many... like saying the same things.
[SPEAKER_02]: To become stronger, to overcome enough, you need some understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding that actually, no matter how important it is, it was inaccessible to you from the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could have not owned it from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason you owned it, the only reason you were attached to it, is because you didn't know that it's impossible to own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you know it's impossible to own, it's like a relief.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah, it's an important door, but it doesn't mean that I'll suffer if I lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nor does it mean that I will be all carried away if I get another one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suppose attachment to child, in that case, that you understand, not... not mine, it means you're actually... how to understand it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, again, first you have to accept it as yours, accept full responsibility for it, for all the feelings you have, and then by becoming stronger than that, you can experience, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, a form of dishonor.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not denying the significance of a child, or significance of a parent, or a mother or a father.
[SPEAKER_01]: But means, you develop yourself further than that significance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Further than the significance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the significant object disappears, eventually, means you're not... you won't be taken by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason, again, why...
[SPEAKER_01]: Anicca from the sūtras is different than anicca that's being taught as taught in the sūtras by Goenka and others.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because you don't actually have to wait for things to cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to see their ending in order to see anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know them that they are impermanent while they're in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why they're impermanent is because they have arisen on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's quite a difficult point for me to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a difficult point and it's a different point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because usually people go, ah, see, see, this tree got destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, what you're experiencing right there and there is the positive experience of a destruction of a tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a present experience, which means, actually, nothing exists.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is another experience right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're concerned about things in the world,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, yes, the destruction of the tree would mean impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: The impermanence from the suttas refers to the impermanence, impermanent nature of your experience, of your five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: But unless the moment when you die, you won't experience their ending.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means anicca from the suttas is different than anicca that you can observe with your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it is different, because if it weren't, you wouldn't need a Buddha to teach anicca and anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could just see it yourself, with your eyes, or hear it with your ears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: I saw it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you see a destruction of a house, again, experience of seeing a destruction of a house has arisen, which means there's no impermanence there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only relative impermanence of a certain house changing its shape.
[SPEAKER_01]: From being a useful arranged shape, useful for inhabiting, now it's a less useful shape of a pile of rubble.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still something you're perceiving, so you just perceive a different perception that you externally explain to yourself as change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see what I mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, ask a question then.
[SPEAKER_02]: You said, you said, what, what, what, what, what has arisen?
[SPEAKER_02]: It is impoverished.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, what do you mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: I actually don't understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, like, again, let's take the example of a house.
[SPEAKER_01]: You look at the house.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have the experience of seeing a house.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not just talking about a house, because it's never just a house.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are always in every situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when you think about a situation that you are not present in, you are present in your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mentally, that's your situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cannot leave yourself out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means there is no objective scientific world everybody talks about.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only world you know is the one you can perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you look at a house, that's the experience of seeing a house.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, somebody starts destroying a house, that's the experience of seeing house being destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's another experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impermanence that the Buddha talks about pertains to the experience of any kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not of the specific house, a tree or a child.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experience in itself is impermanent, because it has a reason on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, when you're experiencing the perception of the house, your experience is known as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result of that, any ownership that you have to your house will disappear, even if that house remains standing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, destroying the house, setting it on fire, makes no difference to the internal impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's another experience out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes, having a house being destroyed can possibly remind you of, if you already know it first, not if you don't know it, that actually it was impermanent to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was impermanent while it was still standing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And look, now it's being destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was always in common.
[SPEAKER_01]: Subject to destruction means it can be destroyed, it will be destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean necessarily it's being destroyed while I'm staring at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see the difference now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, actually, whether the house is impermanent or not, if I don't have experience with that, there's no any...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's irrelevant, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only reason people use, like they say, western science, or they say, oh, everything is impermanent, just observe sensations, everything is constantly changing, is basically to deny the responsibility for it, believing that's the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a completely wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to escape it, you first want to admit that the thing means something to you or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, without abandoning that responsibility, then you can see it as impermanent or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't have to witness or have it destroyed in order to prove to yourself that it was impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meaning, if you needed to prove to yourself externally, means you were never sure about it internally, which means there is no knowledge.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why Buddha taught to observe the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: No?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Never like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would say, you observe parts of the body, like lungs or whatever, different organs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take them out of the context of my body, my strong, healthy body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So to experience disgust, dispassion, in regard to that body.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you just think of a pair of lungs, it's quite disgusting.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly what I have in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think about intestines, and skin, hair, think about that, it will make you experience dispassion, because it's not beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't teach sweeping sensations and be aware of your kneecaps or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it was it was a contemplation, bringing those things to mind, so to experience dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do it long enough, then even when you don't have those things in your mind, just being aware of your body will be seen as those
[SPEAKER_01]: Ugly things.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's very interesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think many people, like, in Thailand, I heard, like, many people, they have a body contemplation and, like, a dead, dead, dead body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's what I'm trying to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's for that reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: As experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because usually people don't think about death, don't want to think about death, don't see death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, seeing a dead body or things of that nature will over remind you
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not be...
[SPEAKER_01]: I cannot escape this.
[SPEAKER_01]: This will happen to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you experience dispassion towards your life, towards life of others.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, oh, it will all end like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a reminder of something that kind of everybody knows at the back of their mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, it's not... Again, there is no wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: People can can go a bit funny in regard to it, because it can be too much of a shock or something, and then they can go mad, as they did in the suttas, when they really
[SPEAKER_01]: Practiced hard contemplation of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha went out for the retreat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Three months later, he came back.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's like, maybe half of the monks left.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's like, what happened to the rest?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, well, they were jumping off the cliffs and stuff, because they were... And he said, okay, well, in that case, practice mindfulness of breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: There won't result in such extreme actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, if somebody does maraṇasati correctly, they can become arahant very quickly, because it's a thorough, direct, forceful dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to be able to hold it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If not, you know, you can go a bit mad.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I did a list.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's very interesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Attachment of the child also, it means that as experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, people think they can deal with attachment by denying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By saying, well, it's not really.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just atoms.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's molecules.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to see, like, the child's body is changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to accept that it's your child.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to accept the responsibility for your feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: You must not deny them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to accept the weight, the significance of having a child.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you can overcome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, the experience is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the impermanence pertains.
[SPEAKER_02]: Experience is impermanent means that experience is changing?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, means it will come to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't see the end, necessarily.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's very impassive little point, that you don't see the end.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Sūtra says, whatever has the nature of arising, has the nature of ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're not witnessing the ceasing, just in its nature, it will be affected by cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will cease to come to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because its nature has manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: For that reason, it will have to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because molecules are changing, not because somebody can come and destroy it, just because it has appeared.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are sankhāderas nibbāna and nippāna?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it true?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: No?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because permanent and impermanent doesn't apply to nibbāna, because nibbāna cannot even be... Any designations apply to things, and nibbāna means surpassing all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, using those designations of permanent and impermanent to nibbāna doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is a, I think, it's Chula Veda, when Bhikkhuni Damodara was answering the questions of her ex-husband, and he was asking, where does this lead?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where does this lead?
[SPEAKER_01]: And they came to a point and said, well, that leads to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, well, where does nibbāna lead?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: He's like, well, the point of your questioning has lost meaning then.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't ask that, because all the designations you use cannot be applied to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, any answer I give you won't make any sense
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, it could be completely misperceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: In Sweden, there's actually at least 32 designations of nibbāna, like describing another show.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, right, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's an example.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, I'm talking about nicca.
Nicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: Permanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I guess, I haven't read that sutra, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you mean, in terms of nibbāna, the other show, uh, cessation of universal delusion,
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you say in that sense, as Hiriku just told me about this sutta, I can see that if you say in that sense, oh, it's permanent, from the point of view of the impermanent that you are living in, then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't say it's permanent, it lasts forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if something... Usually, if people say permanent, they mean eternal.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is a difference there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eternal means, basically, when things are taken as self, it will last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's usually the sense of permanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a soul or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody said nibbāna is permanent, by quoting this sutta, that's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then it should be clarified that it's in the context, from the point of view of the impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if they say nibbāna is permanent, means once you enter it, it lasts forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: That makes no sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the idea of lasting and time
[SPEAKER_01]: cannot pertain to timeless nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, permanent, as pertaining... referring to time, usually, cannot pertain to the timeless nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you use it as epithet to describe it, in which case you should probably clarify it as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not right to say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Saṃsāra is permanent only based on determination, that is, because... Again, it's not... it's not permanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to be occurring for as long as you don't see the nature of it and escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, again, saying permanent or impermanent cannot really designate that correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you're using to inspire somebody, to say them, yeah, from your point of view of this all impermanence, this is the permanent, this is the stable, this is the free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in terms of, if you use permanent as a designation of time, last forever, it doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: What, what is the reason it is impermanent?
[SPEAKER_02]: It is just a law of nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just must understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, what, what is the reason that they experience it?
[SPEAKER_02]: It is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a serious... sometimes... because usually we don't see the beginning and the end.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's quite difficult to see the... You don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to see them correctly, one has a reason is impermanent, because he has a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you have to accept it that what is the reason is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's a fantasy in your thoughts, it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you have to accept responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then through that, you can eventually see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As impermanent for the reasons of manifesting by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you kind of cut short and try to do it before, basically means you'll be... it will become a part of denial.
[SPEAKER_02]: I feel, I think, that the only way to show the impermanence clearly is, suppose, it's like two Christian people who never accept dharma and buddhism.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, then, what we can really clearly explain, just the things are impermanent, and it's quite difficult to explain clearly, but the, like, attention, now, attention changes, the object.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the only way to explain, like, impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't think they'll get it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, first, they would... they have to be willing, whoever, not just Christians, or whoever you're talking, even Buddhists, actually, they have to be willing to hear, they have to be willing to accept that they don't necessarily know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if they think they already know it, whatever you say will fall on deaf ears.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, saying everything is changing, we'll go, OK, so what?
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's closer, probably, to say, well, the fact that you will die, the fact that you don't really know what's after your life, you can't be sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you really want to spend your life based on a mere belief, a mere faith, in an imaginary friend or something like that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot verify.
[SPEAKER_01]: That God exists as such, that heaven exists as such, that Jesus exists as such, that you'll be saved for sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you be sure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you do everything rightly for the rest of your life, as Jesus prescribed, or whoever, in the Bible, you still cannot be 100% sure that that will be the outcome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your entire life, all of your actions, all of your choices will revolve founded, based upon, rooted in faith, in just blind faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: If someone is suffering, suffering, suffering, suffering from sickness, like a terminal, terminal ill, then, eh, if, if they, they, like, ask us, then, how to be free from suffering, of course, in the case of Uttarachandra?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I think it might, it might, it might be a bit late for them at that point.
[SPEAKER_02]: If we just tell them that the things have arisen, it is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they feel like the pain is there every day.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they've been practicing throughout their life, then, yeah, you could remind them of the d
[SPEAKER_01]: But if they haven't, you can't say anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a very difficult point, I think, because even Vedanānyāna really suffered, eh, in sickness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, after pain, there's pain, there's pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Samādhi is real, he's here, he's sick.
[SPEAKER_02]: Real.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because pain is everyday.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is morning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the most you can say to a person who never practiced, at the moment of their death, is to think about good things they've done in their life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Provided they were good things that they've done.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they haven't, well then,
[SPEAKER_01]: Try to think good things now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, it might be a bit late, but obviously...
[SPEAKER_02]: When I'm... when I'm sick, that doesn't mean I observe.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what only I can see as relief is like attention definitely changes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because all the time we never think about the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pain is present all the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: But our... our... we are thinking about many other things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our attention changes, the object of thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only that we went for understanding commonness.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said,
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to keep witnessing the change to understand impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to recognize independent arising of things, arising on their own, in order to recognize impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not impermanent because they will... they're not impermanent because they're going to come to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're already impermanent because they have arisen in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they will have to come to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you stop worrying about cessation of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Start looking in their arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they have arisen, you have no say in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no say in arising your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have some say in what you're going to attend, once it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact is, it will always arise on its own.
[SPEAKER_02]: I heard that Prabhupāda Nārāyaṇī was doing walking meditation on the here earth in prominence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: How to understand?
[SPEAKER_02]: I simply heard that Padma's eyes need to cease.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's quite hard to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you would, you would be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what he kept observing, like an experience, what... Well, he was pondering and reflecting on dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nature of saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nature of determinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nature of arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Three people, and you did an experiment on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you forget that you are the one observing the experiment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are focused on your experiment, you're going to be able to see yourself experimenting.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you see yourself experimenting, you have to... you can stop doing experiments.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can just see yourself doing whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the way you maintain mindfulness means already you see the background, the mood, the... the... the way... how you're feeling, the mental state, the... in the relation to the situation where you... And see how that affects you on a particular level.
[SPEAKER_01]: What it makes you think, what it makes you choose, what it makes you dwell on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it makes you dwell on the bad things, because you're in a bad mood, well, you can choose to dwell on not bad things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can choose to not dwell on bad things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you dwell on good things, while you're in a bad mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: You keep dwelling on good things, or more inspiring things, and yeah, you can change that mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mood is not completely independent from a particular situation either.
[SPEAKER_01]: From a particular...
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts or perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, it's on a different level.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're simultaneously there, but on a different level.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I think, exactly, we don't need to know where this body is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that important, I think, the mood.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that case, this body is now in the court.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that important.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to think about the location, but you have to think about you in the situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is your body in the situation?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether it's you and your kuti, or you're in a tuk-tuk, or you're walking on a path, you, in a certain location, which is what makes the whole situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to be visualizing and thinking about the kuti and the shape of the walls.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to know that you are in that situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the bodily posture is like the first, kind of, first
[SPEAKER_01]: Designation of your situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're seated in such and such place.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're standing in such and such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the most fundamental external output you're in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because while you're seated, you can't have intentions of, you know, based on your standing, or based on your walking, or based on you lying down.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why being aware of your bodily posture, kind of makes you aware of the whole situation already.
[SPEAKER_01]: But being aware of your bodily posture as a background, not as a kind of going, observing sensation.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's actually very difficult that there is a mood, the mental state.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing it as general background is quite hard.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes it appears in front.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if it appears in front, you know that there's something appearing in front, but there is always a background to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that doesn't mean that you lost the sight of your background, unless you got confused.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suppose if the mood is... mood is happy or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is not in front.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see it as background.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say, oh, I am happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that doesn't mean that your back will not change suddenly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can still be happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you shouldn't confuse that you saying, I'm happy, is your happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Happiness is the state of mind which is always in the background.
[SPEAKER_02]: The purpose of the practice is to understand the intention of the... Well, yeah, to overcome it.
[SPEAKER_02]: To understand it, to overcome it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By recognizing that things arise on their own, by not being moved by your moods, wholesome or unwholesome, you end up, like, well, you stop appropriating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, ah, this thing doesn't require sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense of self becomes part of that mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Me just becomes part of that whole picture of background and of general and particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by not knowing general and particular, you were centered on yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you recognize this operates without the self, so the center from yourself is removed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when the center is not in the self, that's not self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, the self, if really I believe in self like that, actually, I see clearly, actually, self becomes incommon.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, suppose, because where this body is in, actually, according to the situation, where this body is in, actually, the rule changes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means, like, it's quite strange that if that is really self, then...
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't change.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have... it's something that needs to be... you have to dwell on it, on and on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the self is not... you see it once, you have to keep dwelling on it, that it cannot be owned, that it's subject to cessation because it's already there, because you have no say in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you dwell on it long enough, then you'll stop feeling its mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means there's no meaning that to keep seeing that it's arising intentionally.
[SPEAKER_02]: It has already... it is the given... given the intention, so it is not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I keep observing, there's no point of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there is no point because if you do it like that, you end up not taking responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you have to learn how to always be responsible for that, and then you can start saying, yeah, this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through that responsibility, not before.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, order of things is important.
[SPEAKER_01]: All externally might be the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, this doesn't belong to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you said it before, you took full responsibility, or after.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you said before, means you obscure the responsibility, you obscure the feeling, you obscure the karma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you do it after, then, ah, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without abandoning, which means you don't do it for the reasons
[SPEAKER_01]: of avoiding responsibility, which is why people do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you accept responsibility, you don't fear responsibility, no matter how fearful it is, and then you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it can apply to responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you want to avoid responsibility and do it, there's nothing, because it can only apply to responsibility, but because you avoid it, there's nothing to apply to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you end up just keep doing, keep saying, keep denying, but it doesn't really lead anywhere, or leads to more frustration, usually.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe it's praying that, like, suppose there is God.